Women's Action Alliance Records, 1970-1996
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Women's Action Alliance records
1970 - 1996
Women's Action Alliance
MS 363
318 boxes (117.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Women's advocacy organization and feminist collective. The extensive WAA records are a rich source of information about the contemporary women's movement and the dynamics of race and class within it. The organization's projects focused on such issues as coalition-building among women's groups, women's economic development, teenage pregnancy prevention, and non-sexist child development. The WAA Records document the administration of the organization, its projects, and its role as a women's information clearinghouse. Materials include correspondence, publications, resource files, photographs, and audiovisual materials.
The Women's Action Alliance (WAA) was founded in 1971 to coordinate resources for organizations and individuals involved in the women's movement on the grass-roots level. Founders included Gloria Steinem (see also the Gloria Steinem Papers), Brenda Feigen, and Catherine Samuels. The organization's original mission was "to stimulate and assist women at the local level to organize around specific action projects aimed at eliminating concrete manifestations of economic and social discrimination." Conceived of as an advisory service that could provide back-up support, "the choice and objectives and basic strategy" of such initiatives would be "made by the group in every case."
In the early years, several well-known figures - including Bella Abzug, Shirley Chisholm, John Kenneth Galbraith, and Maya Miller -- were appointed to the Alliance's board of directors. While these figures contributed largely just the weight of their association, other board members -- like Franklin Thomas and Cory Eklund -- gave a great deal of energy to the Alliance. Over the years, Gloria Steinem's efforts were considerable, and at times crucial, to the organization's very survival. Steinem chaired the board from l97l to l978 and subsequently assisted on fundraising projects benefiting the Alliance.
During the first three years of the Alliance, the executive directors changed almost annually, with Brenda Feigen, Grace Helen McCabe, and Marlene Krauss serving. In l974 the WAA hired Ruth J. Abram, formerly a project director with the American Civil Liberties Union and executive director of the Norman Foundation. Abram, who served for five years, developed close ties to the foundation and corporate grants community, and their grants to the Alliance were often their first to a feminist organization. Her fundraising expertise resulted in a more than six-fold increase in the organization's budget. During Abram's tenure, the National Women's Agenda Coalition, Women at Work Fairs, and the Women's History Institute were organized.
Abram resigned in 1979 and was succeeded by Arlie C. Scott. Coming to the WAA after a long association with the National Organization for Women, including a term as national vice president, Scott saw the Alliance through a period of increasingly shrinking budgets. Staff and project plans shrunk as well. In early l982, after two years as executive director, Scott took an extended leave of absence from the WAA, never to return.
Sylvia Kramer was hired as executive director in the fall of l982. As the Alliance started its second decade, Kramer, a former teacher, placed greater emphasis on educational programs directed at older children (e.g. the Computer Equity Project and the Portable Women's History Project). The organization continued to focus on women's centers and economic opportunity for women as well. By the late 1980s, the WAA had three major arms: the Non-Sexist Childhood Development Project (under whose auspices projects like the 1988 study of "Children of Single Parents in the Schools" were carried out), the Women's Centers Project (the WAA helped establish the National Association of Women's Centers in 1986), and Information Services, which continued to provide reference and referral services for WAA's broad constituency.
Beginning in the late 1980s and continuing on through the 1990s, the WAA began to place greater emphasis on women's health issues, launching initiatives such as the 1987-88 Teenage Pregnancy Prevention Project, the Women's Alcohol and Drug Education Project, the Resource Mothers Program, and the Women's Centers and AIDS Project. Shazia Rafi became Executive Director in 1991.
Karel R. Amarath became the WAA's final executive director in 1993. Amarath worked with the Board of Directors to restructure the organization, making it more internally organized and fiscally aware. Gender equity initiatives continued to emphasize education and health care. The Computer Equity Expert Project (C.E.E.P) targeted more than 200 schools nationwide, reaching nearly 10,000 educators and almost 80,000 students. The Task Force on Integrated Projects (T.F.I.P) worked with pregnant and parenting adolescent and adult single parent mothers and their children, while the Women's Alcohol & Drug Education Project continued to assist African-American and Caribbean women, and Latinas, reaching more than four hundred women and girls annually.
By the mid-1990s, the WAA had become largely dependent on New York City and state budgets for its funding. The organization was dealt a severe blow in August 1995, when, on the eve of their twenty-fifth anniversary, their funding was cut by 65% with just thirty days notice. The Women's Alcohol and Drug Education Project, for example, one of the WAA's most successful programs at that time, lost $350,000 in funding, spelling the end of some twenty training sites in New York State. With more than half of their support removed, the organization hired development consultants to try to replace the funding, meanwhile looking for "neighbors" with whom to share space and rent. However, the WAA ultimately found it impossible to recover; in June 1997, by a vote of the Board of Directors, the Women's Action Alliance was dissolved.
The breadth and scope of the WAA projects are indicative of the diversity of the women's movement itself. The most successful projects include the Information and Reference Service, the Non-Sexist Childhood Development Project (NSCD), and the National Women's Agenda and Women's Centers Projects.
The WAA's main modus operandi was to identify a problem, question, or population with specific needs; formulate and distribute a questionnaire exploring the activities and needs of groups or individuals concerned with the issue in question; and summarize the results in a directory, guide, or manual. As a result, scattered throughout the records of the WAA and its many initiatives are caches of replies, reports, and data on far-ranging subjects.
A significant proportion of this material documents the activities of a large number of women's centers, projects, and services across the U.S. and abroad, from the mid 1970s to the mid 1980s. By 1974 the WAA had begun to collect and preserve files tracking such activities, while the production of the "Practical Guide to the Women's Movement" and subsequent directories, organized both by geographic location and by program area, also involved the distribution and return of questionnaires in which women's centers and service organizations outlined their services, objectives, and goals. Vertical files in the reference collections of the WAA library, organized alphabetically by state and generated in connection with the "Practical Guide to the Women's Movement," preserve these profiles together with associated correspondence and literature. Another set, generated by the Women's Center Project, is housed with the records of that initiative.
The WAA's work with women's centers illustrates the organization's Byzantine nature, in that some of the WAA's initiatives were conceived by one department, launched by another, and administered by a third, with records and files shared and transferred between offices. Thus, in some cases, records pertaining to a significant issue embraced by the WAA are distributed throughout several series. For example, from the National Women's Agenda Project (SERIES II. PROJECTS) sprung the idea to create a networking service and national directory for local women's centers across the country. When the NWAP folded in 1980, the "Women's Centers Project" was created to take its place, offering networking and technical assistance programs. Eventually, the directory was compiled and printed. The organizational profiles gathered in this effort were preserved in the WAA library (SERIES III. RESOURCES-Library-Reference collections-Vertical files), while material pertaining to the actual publication, Women Helping Women: A State-by-State Directory of Services (1981) is found in SERIES III. RESOURCES-Library-Publications.
As the organization evolved and matured, projects were increasingly launched by the WAA and then handed off to largely independent staff who carried them through. For that reason, records of some WAA programs (e.g. Buddies Exploring Science Together (BEST) and the Women and AIDS project) are either represented by a very small amount of material, or not represented at all. By 1993, for example, of the WAA's fifteen paid staff people, six worked outside the organization's Lexington Avenue headquarters, in the South Bronx office of the Citizens Advice Bureau, Brooklyn's Medgar Evers College, and even Mujeres Latinos en Accion, based in Chicago, though there are no materials preserved here from the South Bronx, Brooklyn or Chicago personnel. For these reasons, the records fully document the organization's growth and development through the 1970s and 1980s, but contain comparatively little material from the 1990s. Records pertaining to the dissolution of the WAA will not be available until 2004, after they are released by the law firm that served the organization.
In as many places as possible, elements of the WAA's filing system were preserved. For example, the general subject files kept by the Executive Director's office, as well as those kept by Ruth Abram, arrived nearly intact, and each set has been left in its original order. A large series of files containing information on potential funders has also been preserved (SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Development and fundraising). By and large, however, the records of the various WAA projects and programs came in different levels of organization, reflecting in part the decentralized structure of the organization. In addition, the records reflect the idiosyncrasies of an ever-changing cast of project directors and administrative assistants. The present arrangement of the records, especially in the case of administrative files, reflect our effort to achieve some consistency across and between programs.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Administration
II. Projects
III. Resources
IV. Photographs
V. Audiovisual Material
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, with the following restrictions:
Researchers wishing to consult Boxes 256-267, which includes incoming and outgoing reference correspondence, must sign an Access Agreement Form in which they agree to refrain from making public any information that would identify a correspondent.
Box 46, which contains information on staff terminations and evaluations, is closed to research until 2020.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
Portions of the Women's Action Alliance Records are available on microfilm in the Sophia Smith Collection and in the circulating collection of Neilson Library. The latter is available on interlibrary loan. A reel guide is also available. Contact the SSC for more information.
Selections from the Women's Action Alliance Records can be viewed in the Web exhibit Agents of Social Change: New Resources on 20th-century Women's Activism.
History of the Collection
The Women's Action Alliance began donating their records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1987.
Search Terms
Feigen, Brenda; Steinem, Gloria; Abortion services--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Abused women--Services for--United States--History--Sources; Child care--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Computers and women; Discrimination against the handicapped--United States; Early childhood education--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminists--United States--20th century--Sources; Handicapped--Education--United States--History--20th century; Handicapped women--United States; Institute on Women's History--Sources; Maternal health services--United States--History--20th century--Sources; National Association of Women's Centers; National Women's Agenda Project; National Women's Conference (1st: 1977: Houston, Tex.); Sex discrimination in education--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Sexism in mass media; Sex discrimination in employment--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Sex discrimination against women--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Sports for women--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Substance abuse--Prevention--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Substance abuse--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Teenage pregnancy--United States--History--20th century--Sources; United States. Job Training Partnership Act--History--Sources; Women--Economic conditions--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women's Educational Equity Act Program (U.S.)--History--Sources; Women's Action Alliance; Women's Agenda (periodical); Women--Education--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material can be found in the Gloria Steinem Papers, Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1971-96, 32.25 linear ft.
  This series documents the general operations of the WAA. The Alliance was run by a Board of Directors and an Executive Director together with administrative and project staff. Its activities were financed by federal, state, and New York City governments as well as corporate and foundation grants and individual donations. The series consists of general administrative records and those of the Executive Director, the Board of Directors, the Development office, Publicity and Public Education department and other WAA officers and staff.
  General
  Materials in this subseries reflect the overall operations of the WAA, including the Articles of Incorporation and related documents, fact sheets, mission statement, and annual and quarterly reports. Of particular interest are several reviews of the organization, some in-house and others by consultants, which provide insight into the WAA's growth and challenges from the 1970s and early 1980s. Some especially illuminating documents are Catherine Samuels' circa 1974 summaries of the evolution of the women's movement, 1971-74, and the movement's "goals, ideology and strategies," which she hoped would inform the future direction of the WAA.
  Board of Directors
  Materials from the Board of Directors is arranged in five sections: General, Chairs, Committee work, Membership, and Minutes. Four members of the Board - Gloria Steinem, Joan Shigekawa, Catherine Samuels, and Kay Ellen Consolver - served as Chairs. In these cases, the material pertaining to their chairmanship and their board membership more generally is collected under Chairs, organized chronologically according to each individual's dates of tenure. In most cases, this material is mainly correspondence and scattered biographical information, though Catherine Samuels' files from her service on the American Revolution Bicentennial Administration as well as her own subject files are preserved here. Of particular interest is her unpublished paper "The Evolution of the Women's Movement, 1971-74," as well as a folder of material on consciousness-raising.
  Material related to Committee work is mainly correspondence, minutes, and memoranda from the several committees that helped run the WAA. The bulk of this material, however, was generated by the WAA's Executive Committee. Membership contains lists, addresses, and individual files containing correspondence and biographical material of board members.
  The largest amount of material pertaining to the Board is Minutes from the Board of Directors and Executive Committee annual, quarterly, and monthly meetings. Board of Directors minutes, including annual, quarterly, and special meetings, are filed chronologically. They contain general program and financial information as well as summaries and reports on different WAA projects. Pertinent local, national, global, personnel, and occasionally personal issues are addressed in various board minutes and staff reports and memoranda.
  Executive Directors
  Papers pertaining to the Executive Directors are organized in two sections that preserve the original order of this office's files. The first, the Executive Director's General office files, contain correspondence, ordered chronologically, from directors Brenda Feigen Fasteau (1971-72; including several letters containing advice on organizing from Elizabeth Forsling Harris), Grace Helen McCabe (1972-73), and Marlene Krauss (1973-74). There is some correspondence pertaining to the Board of Directors, though the bulk of this material reflects the Executive Directors' role in fundraising. General materials also include subject files kept by the office of the Executive Director.
  Beginning with the tenure of Ruth J. Abram (1974-79), the amount of material preserved grows greatly, and so the tenures of Abram and her successors Arlie Scott (1979-82); Sylvia Kramer (1982-91); and Karel R. Amarath, (1993-97) are filed separately, as Individuals. There is no material related to the tenure of Shazia Rafi (circa 1991-93).
  Public relations and education
  The subseries is arranged in four parts: General, Press coverage, Promotion, and Public Interest Public Relations (PIPR), the latter being the public relations firm engaged by the WAA to help promote its programs. Material here includes clippings collected by the WAA on programs and events in which it participated as well as outreach efforts such as press releases and advertising. The material pertaining to PIPR is generally related to the retention of the firm (including contracts and correspondence) but includes as well some media advisories, press releases, and fact sheets developed by the firm for the WAA's use.
  Staff
  Records pertaining to the WAA staff illuminate the day-to-day operations of the WAA, including its office procedures and general employment policies. Sections here include General, Intra-office communication, Meetings, Personnel, Policy development, and Project directors. Especially interesting are the minutes and memoranda from staff meetings, revealing the particular tensions that arose in an organization striving to put feminism into practice in the workplace. Sets of floorplans illuminate the physical setting in which these tensions played out. Access to material pertaining to personnel issues and salaries is restricted.
  Development
  This documents the organization's ongoing efforts to secure financial support for both specific projects and programs and its general operation. It is arranged as follows: General, Fundraising, Funders, and Proposals. Files pertaining to fundraising and development are also found throughout the records associated with individual programs and projects; materials in this subseries reflect the work of the central WAA office.
  General records include the correspondence and subject/research files of Director of Development Donna Meade and Development Coordinator Sally Li Young, research and correspondence on past and potential contributors, and the Development office's subject files. Especially interesting, filed under "research," are reports and papers illuminating general issues related to women and philanthropy, including "The Women's Movement and Foundations," a transcript of a 17 September 1971 symposium involving Brenda Feigen Fasteau, Marjorie Fine, Eleanor Holmes Norton, and Gloria Steinem among others; and the 1982 report "Inequality of Sacrifice: The Impact of the Reagan Budget on Women." Material pertaining to Fundraising includes records from annual individual, foundation and corporate fundraising campaigns and records from fundraising events, including the WAA's annual celebrity "Roasts."
  The Funders section comprises the WAA's extensive set of files of potential funders. These files, arranged alphabetically, contain annual reports from potential foundation and corporate funding sources, and correspondence. In several cases, proposals, particularly related to the 1990s campaign to fund the Women's Alcohol and Drug Education Project, were also filed here; these have been left in their original order to preserve this late usage of these files, though in general, proposals seeking both general operating support and funding for specific programs are housed in the section devoted to Proposals.
  Financial
  The Financial records of the WAA document the organization's finances from 1972 to 1993. They are arranged as follows: Financial statements and audits, Budget information, and Income. Annual financial statements produced by independent auditors, organized chronologically, provide an overview of the WAA's financial status. The contents of intact budget books for 1975-77 provide an exceptionally complete view of the WAA's finances for those years. Records pertaining to the WAA's income include royalty statements, a savings account passbook, and tax records.
- SERIES II. PROJECTS 1972-96, 63.75 linear ft.
  Throughout its history the WAA initiated projects and programs intended to address "concrete manifestations of discrimination." This series, containing material generated by those varied initiatives, is broken down into five subseries, representing the general areas in which the WAA was active: Economics, Education (including the Non-Sexist Child Development Project), Health, and Coalitions. The latter is comprised of the National Women's Agenda Project and the Women's Centers Project. Researchers interested in a specific program may also want to consult the general support proposals in SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Development, as these often include year-end reviews of program activities.
  Economics
  Economic Development Project (1980-84), 1.75 linear ft.
  In the fall of 1982, The Women's Action Alliance formed an advisory committee of economic development experts. The goal of this committee was to obtain funding from large corporations and foundations which would support an Economic Development Project. Under the direction of Sara Gould, the EDP's goals were: 1) to act as a resource for women's social service organizations seeking greater economic self-sufficiency, and 2) to increase the economic self-sufficiency of women's nonprofit service organizations through improved management practices and the development of income-generating projects and activities. The EDP researched, advised, and communicated with a variety of women's groups, and published a handbook, Struggling Through Tight Times. The Economic Development Project was ultimately unable to continue due to insufficient funding, and ended in June 1984.
  The Economic Development Project's records are arranged in the following sections: Administrative, Conferences and travel, Fundraising and foundations, Groups, and Resources.
  Non-traditional Occupations for Women (1977-86), 1.5 linear ft.